Inventory of the Fr. P. Mönkemöller collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Fr. P. Mönkemöller collection
1914-1920
26006
Hoover Institution Archives
59 manuscript boxes, 15 oversize boxes, 4 oversize folders (54.6 linear feet)
Pamphlets, leaflets, proclamations, orders, memoranda, reports, newspaper issues, maps, photographs, and postcards relating to German military operations during World War I; political, social, and economic conditions in Germany during the war; war relief; war propaganda; prisoners of war; the German Revolution of 1918-1919; and the elections of 1920 in Germany.
Mönkemöller, Fr. P.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1926.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Fr. P. Mönkemöller collection contains pamphlets, leaflets, proclamations, orders, memoranda, reports, newspaper issues, maps, photographs, and postcards relating to German military and civilian life before, during, and after World War I. The majority of the collection pertains to the Central Powers’ military operations during World War I, on both the Western and Eastern Fronts. Photographs, propaganda, and other printed matter, such as newsletters, document the activities of soldiers serving in World War I.
The collection also widely documents the conditions in prisoner of war camps through publications created by prisoners, including newsletters, flyers, and theatrical programs. These materials also reflect the diversity of prisoners, with publications written in German, French, Russian, Armenian, Turkish, Urdu, and Hindi.
Aspects of civilian life in Germany during the war, especially food rationing, are another major theme of the materials. The collection contains broadsides, leaflets, and brochures informing citizens of food shortages and techniques for gathering and preserving food. Other subjects that are reflected to a lesser extent include the German Revolution of 1918 and the 1920 elections.
Arrangement Statement
The Fr. P. Mönkemöller collection maintains the original intellectual order devised by its collector, Fr. P. Mönkemöller, although it has been physically rearranged in some cases to accommodate items needing special housing due to their size. Mönkemöller arranged the materials into fourteen sections based on format or subject and referred to these groups as "lists." These lists are further divided into subsections.
A detailed inventory of the collection was created by Mönkemöller and is available on the register shelf in the archives reading room and as a searchable PDF supplement to this document. It is important to note that not all items listed in the inventory can be found in the collection itself. Mönkemöller physically marked each item in the collection with a number that corresponds to a description in the inventory. The description may be for an individual item or a group of similar items. In the inventory, these numbers typically start over at “1” with each new subsection of a list, although on the items themselves the numbering continues sequentially. The original inventory was heavily annotated by archives staff to continue this numbering system between the subsections and designate the items that are in fact in the collection.
Five new sections were added later as an increment and are not reflected in Mönkemöller's inventory. These sections include Memorabilia, the Czibor Collection, the Viv Watson Collection, a Subject File, and Printed Matter. These sections have been arranged by format.
To use the collection, researchers should consult the original inventory first, and then locate materials of interest in the Hoover Institution’s box level inventory. Since Mönkemöller often grouped multiple items together as one intellectual entity, it is possible that in some cases one “item,” if of different sizes, may be in multiple boxes. The removal and rehousing of large or fragile materials has been indicated by separation sheets placed in the boxes.
Elections--Germany.; Germany--Economic conditions.; Germany--History--1918-1933.; Germany--History--Revolution, 1918.; Germany--Politics and government.; Prisoners of war.; Propaganda, German.; World War, 1914-1918--Causes.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Germany.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1914-1918--Propaganda.
- Original inventory to the Mönkemöller collection, circa 1920 (Box 59)
  PDF of Inventory
  Downloadable PDF file of the original inventory to the Fr. P. Mönkemöller collection
- List I:
  - 17, 21, 28, 59, 70, 73, 143, 175, 179, 180, 186, 196, 210, 222, 224, 228, 244, 251-253, 259, 261, 266, 268, 297, 304, 316, 320, 323, 338-339, 342-343, 349, 363, 384-385, 396 (Box 42)
  - 397, 405, 419, 427, 433, 437, 510, 518, 520 (Box 43)
  - 542-546, 548-549, 622-633, 635-742, 743-752, 754-765 (Box 1, Box 70, Box 73)
  - 766-781, 783-789, 791-829 (Box 2, Box 70, Box 73)
  - 830-848, 942-943, 945-1113, 1114-1143, 1144-1165, 1177-1200 (Box 3, Box 70, Box 73)
  - 1177-1270, 1272-1286 (Box 4, Box 70, Box 73)
  - 1287, 1393-1396 (Box 5, Box 72)
  - 1398-1445 (Box 6, Box 70)
  - 1460, 1462-1475, 1476-1490 (Box 7, Box 70, Box 73)
- List II:
  - 14, 16, 23, 40, 46, 49, 65-67, 72, 95, 122, 131-132 (Box 43)
  - 133, 135, 148-149, 152, 155-156, 158, 161, 163, 169-170, 172, 174, 196-197, 200, 202, 208, 210, 214 (Box 44)
  - 215, 217, 219-221, 223, 225, 228, 230, 233-234, 237, 240, 244, 265, 268-269, 272, 274-275 (Box 45)
  - 222, 277-279, 281-284, 286, 294-295, 297-299, 301, 304-305, 310, 322-323 (Box 46)
  - 329, 333-334, 337, 343-345, 349, 353, 355-361, 364-367, 369-370, 373, 375, 377-378, 382, 387, 390 (Box 47)
  - 395, 399, 405-408, 410-411, 415, 419-420, 432, 440-443, 455-456, 461-462 (Box 48)
  - 464-465, 467-475, 476, 477, 479-480, 481, 483-486, 491, 495-496, 498-507 (Box 49)
  - 507-508, 510, 512-514, 516-518, 520, 522, 524-525, 529-532, 534-535, 537-540 (Box 50)
- List III:
  - 14, 17, 26-27 (Box 50)
  - 35, 40, 45, 82, 102-103 (Box 51)
  - 113-117 (Box 7, Box 70, Box 73)
  - 124, 126-129, 257-263 (Box 8, Box 70, Box 72, Box 73)
  - 264-271 (Box 9, Box 72, Box 73)
  - 288, 290, 294 (Box 54)
- List IV:
  - 66-68, 80, 89-90, 384, 386, 525, 552 (Box 9, Box 70)
  - 560-562, 628-668, 672-673, 681-689 (Box 10, Box 70)
- List V:
  - 1-40 (Box 10, Box 72, Box 73)
  - 21-194 (Box 11, Box 72, Box 70)
  - 195-350, 501-553 (Box 12, Box 70, Box 72, Box 73)
  - 362, 415, 422, 427-428, 431, 434, 436-437, 439, 443, 455-457, 460, 463, 465, 467, 468, 470, 471 (Box 51)
  - 363, 426, 430, 432-433, 474-476, 480-483, 495-496, 498-499 (Box 52)
  - 554-606, 607 (Box 13, Box 70, Box 73)
  - 608 (Box 52)
  - 609-615, 617-625, 627 (Box 13, Box 72, Box 73)
  - 626, 628-631, 634-638, 672-683, 685-715 (Box 14, Box 73)
  - 717, 719-720, 722, 724, 734, 736, 742 (Box 52)
  - 746-750 (Box 14)
  - 751-770 (Box 15, Box 70, Box 73, Map case)
  - 771-778 (Box 70)
- List VI:
  - 12 (Box 15, Box 52)
  - 37-38, 45-53 (Box 56)
  - 54 (Box 15)
  - 55-57, 59-71 (Box 56)
  - 75-83, 85 (Box 15)
  - 88, 90-92 (Box 57)
  - 101, 103 (Box 15)
  - 106-108 (Box 57)
  - 109 (Box 15)
  - 111 (Box 57)
  - 113 (Box 15)
  - 114 (Box 16)
  - 115 (Box 57)
  - 116-175 (Box 16, Box 70)
  - 176-177 (Box 57)
  - 187-199 (Box 16, Box 73)
  - 209, 211-236, 348 (Box 17)
- List VII:
  - 37-38 (Box 52)
  - 39-81, 85-88, 93-97 (Box 17, Box 53, Box 54, Box 71, Box 73)
  - 106-108, 110-111, 115 (Box 54)
  - 120-123 (Box 17)
  - 129-132, 135-144, 146-167, 169-173 (Box 18, Box 71, Box 72)
  - 176-177 (Box 54)
  - 179-183, 188-211, 213-238, 247, 249-250 (Box 19, Box 71)
  - 248, 253, 255-259 (Box 20)
  - 260 (Box 58)
  - 261-267 (Box 20, Box 71)
  - 268-269, 272-275, 282-289 (Box 54)
  - 290 (Box 55)
  - 297 (Box 20)
  - 308, 319 (Box 55)
  - 326-332, 335, 341-342 (Box 20, Box 72)
  - 343 (Box 58)
  - 344-346 (Box 20)
  - 347-355, 365-377 (Box 21)
  - 378 (Box 58)
  - 379 (Box 21)
  - 380 (Box 58)
  - 381-384 (Box 21)
  - 385-404 (Box 22)
  - 405-410 (Box 21)
  - 422-431, 433-439 (Box 22)
  - 436-441 (Box 23)
  - 442 (Box 58)
  - 443-463, 468 (Box 23, Box 71)
  - 469 (Box 24)
  - 478, 483-484 (Box 55)
  - 485-487, 489-490, 493, 496, 498-517, 515-517 (Box 24, Box 25, Box 72)
  - 518 (Box 55)
  - 526 (Box 58)
  - 549-552, 554-593 (Box 25)
  - 594-598 (Box 26)
- List VIII:
  - 22, 38, 120-121, 142, 157, 235, 237, 248, 258-259 (Box 55)
  - 260, 380, 434, 442, 526, 646, 678 (Box 56)
- List IX:
  - 284, 296-298, 300-303, 305-310 (Box 26)
  - 311-320 (Box 27, Box 71)
- List X:
  - 395 (Box 63-65)
  - 396 (Box 63-68)
  - 405, 410-412, 506, 607-608 (Box 27, Box 69, Box 71)
  - 609-614, 616 (Box 28, Box 71, Box 73, Box 74)
  - 618 (Box 74)
  - 619-620 (Box 28, Box 71)
  - 620-622 (Box 29, Box 71)
  - 622-624 (Box 30, Box 71, Box 72)
  - 624 (Box 31, Box 73)
  - 626-627 (Box 74)
  - 648-649, 664, 667 (Box 32)
  - Mönkemöller Photograph Collection
    - 1-305: General World War I military operations (Box 34-36)
    - 306-375: German royalty and military leaders (Box 36)
    - 376-650: Western Front: General
    - 651-760: Western Front: Belgium
    - 761-780: Western Front: France, Chemin des Dames
    - 781-800: Western Front: France, Marne
    - 801-825: Western Front: France, Marne (Box 37)
    - 826-840: Western Front: France, Montdidier-Noyon
    - 841-900: Western Front: Finland (Box 37)
    - 901-1076: Eastern Front: General
    - 1077-1123: Eastern Front: Caucausus, Tiflis
    - 1124-1150: Eastern Front: Macedonia
    - 1151-1175: Eastern Front: Poland, Warsaw
    - 1176-1192: Eastern Front: Turkey and Palestine
    - 1193-1285: Eastern Front: Ukraine
    - 1286-1308: General World War I military operations
    - 1309-1377: General World War I military operations (Box 62)
  - "Kriegspostkarten" postcards
    - 4, 7, 9, 13, 28, 43, 45, 47, 49, 51-54, 58, 60, 62, 64-68, 82, 84, 86 (Box 37)
    - 87, 89, 100, 101-104, 107-109 (Box 38)
  - "Ansichtspostkarten" postcards
    - 2, 9, 12-13, 16, 18, 20-21, 23, 25-29, 32, 35, 42-43, 46-48, 51-55 (Box 38)
- List XI:
  - 20-21 (Box 32, Box 71)
  - 200-209 (Box 31, Box 71, Box 72)
  - 211-213 (Box 33, Box 73)
  - 214-215 (Box 34, Box 73)
  - 216 (Box 33, Box 73)
  - 217-219 (Box 34, Box 73)
  - 220, 223-224, 226-228, 230-238 (Box 31, Box 71, Box 72, Box 73)
  - 239-247, 317-318, 431 (Box 32, Box 71, Box 72)
- List XII:
  - 5, 8, 16, 22-23, 62, 67, 90 (Box 56)
  - 110, 136, 149, 160-165, 186, 194, 198, 202-204, 214, 381, 398, 411 (Box 57)
  - 409 (Box 33)
  - 411 (Box 60)
  - 415-416 (Box 58)
  - 431 (Box 35)
- List XIII:
  - 145-167, 169-176, 183, 185, 200-201 (Box 33, Box 71)
  - 202-204 (Box 34, Box 71, Box 73)
  - 211-213, 216 (Box 33, Box 73)
  - 228, 230, 233, 251, 258, 264-265, 270-271, 283, 288, 293, 314-315 (Box 58)
  - 376 (Box 34)
  - 378, 391, 394, 396, 400, 402, 404-405, 410 (Box 58)
- List XIV (Box 34, Box 36, 58-59)
- Memorabilia, 1910s
  - Catalogs, undated (Box 39)
  - Coaster, undated
  - Commemorative card sets, circa 1914-1915
  - Drawings, undated
  - Field stove, undated
  - Metal stakes, undated
  - Postal cancellation stamps, 1915-1918 (Box 40)
  - Receipt book, undated
- Czibor Collection, 1914-1915
  - Leaflets and posters related to Hungary, 1914-1915 (Box 40)
- Viv Watson Collection, 1914-1915
  - Photographs and transcripts of proclamations, 1914-1915 (Box 40)
- Subject File, 1919-1920
  - Kapp Putsch, 1919-1920 (Box 40, Box 76, Map case)
  - East and West Prussian referendum, 1919-1920 (Box 40, Box 76, Map case)
  - Russian art, 1920s (Box 40, Box 70)
- Printed Matter, 1903-1938
  - Flyers, 1903-1932 (Box 40)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1915-1938 (Box 41)
  - Pamphlets, 1914-1923
  - Theatrical programs from prisoner of war camps, 1915-1918
  - Food rationing proclamations, 1916-1919 (Box 60-61)